A Guide to the Papers of Louis I. Jaffé, 1818 (ca. 1919-1974)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Louis I. Jaffé 1818 (ca. 1919-1974)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9924-b
Ca. 1471 items in 4 boxes (1.3 shelf ft.), and 5 oversize folios.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This addition to the Louis I. Jaffé Papers was a gift from Mrs. Louis I. Jaffé on 12 February 1975.
Biographical/Historical Information
Louis I. Jaffé was born in Detroit, Michigan, February 22, 1888, the son of Phillip and Lotta Maria (Kahn) Jaffé. When Jaffé was twelve years old, his family moved to Durham, North Carolina, and he graduated from high school there in 1907. In 1911, he received an A.B. degree from Trinity College (now Duke University).
While a student at Trinity, Jaffé edited The Chronicle, a campus weekly, and was associate editor of The Archive, a college monthly. After graduation, he joined the staff of the Durham Sun, but left a short time later to become a reporter and assistant city editor for the Richmond Times- Dispatch.
In 1917, Jaffé was commissioned as Second Lieutenant in the Field Artillery Section, Officer's Reserve Corps of the United States Army. He was re-commissioned in the Aviation Section 1918, and again in 1919 with the Service of Supply. He was honorably discharged in France, March 29, 1919, and was commissioned as Inspector in the American National Red Cross with rank of Captain. He served on the Red Cross Commission to the Balkans from April to July, 1919, and was director of the Red Cross News Service in Paris from July to October, 1919. He was made a Chevalier of the State of Roumania, and honor bestowed in recognition of his work there with the Red Cross Commission.
After the war, Jaffé went to Norfolk to become editor of the Virginian-Pilot, a position he held from 1919 until his death in 1950. He was prominent among Virginia liberal journalists and won the Pulitzer Prize in 1929 for an editorial deploring a lynching which took place in Houston, Texas, on the eve of the Democratic National Convention.
In one of his last editorials, dated February 25, 1950, concerning the "mercy killing" of the Boothe bill for desegregation of Virginia public transportation he wrote: "The Virginia Democratic organization makes haste slowly in the field of social-political reform...It is still too uneasy about the impact of de-segregation on common carries to give the proposal anything like an official blessing. That will come later-after a longer look at this highly desirable reform, and possibly after another shove or two from the Supreme Court of the United States."
Scope and Content
This addition to the Louis I. Jaffé Papers, 1818 (ca. 1919-1974), consists of ca. 1471 items (1.3 shelf ft.), including Jaffé's correspondence files "A" through "D," photographs, and several miscellaneous items. The correspondence contains information on a wide variety of topics including the role of a free press and its relations to political partisanship, prohibition, the Virginia anti-lynching bill, promotion of better race relations, the teaching of evolution, and the economy.
Jaffé's correspondence with Harry Byrd contains 11 items and includes discussion of Byrd's consolidation program, his support of the anti-lynching bill, state and federal politics and expansion of the state franchise.
Other items of possible interest include a signed autograph letter from Gertrude Stein to M.A. Agelasto, 1934 [Nov. 11]; a typed manuscript (copy) article on J.J. Lankes by [Louis Jaffé] with holograph comments on the sides and top by Robert Frost, 1941 Nov. 9; The Book Dial, vol. VI, no. 4, which contains articles and woodcuts by J.J. Lankes, 1931 June 1-1932 April 10, with woodcuts enclosed; and a collection of bookplates, 1930-1942 and n.d., and Christmas cards, 1934-1950, by J.J. Lankes.
Arrangement
The correspondence file is alphabetically arranged in boxes one through four. Correspondence designated as "brief or less important" by Mrs. Jaffé has been grouped alphabetically within general folders. Each general group precedes the folders designated for separate individuals.
The correspondence file is followed by a miscellaneous section in box 4. The miscellaneous correspondence is alphabetically arranged and is followed by the miscellaneous items, also arranged alphabetically. The photographs are at the end of box 4.
Contents List
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people whose last names begin with "A" 1925-1949, 26 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with William S. Abell 1949 Jan. 10-May 2, 10 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Randolph G. Adams 1923 Jan. 18-1931 Dec. 2, 8 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Dr. Edward A. Alderman and Mrs. Alderman 1919 Dec. 16-1931 May 1, 16 items (Box 1)
- Corespondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Lt. Col. Henry W. Anderson 1919 Nov. 12-1954 Jan. 9, 10 items (Box 1)
  includes newsclippings and a photograph
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Sherwood Anderson 1930 Aug.-1941 Dec. 21, n.d., 44 items (Box 1)
  including some correspondence from Eleanor Anderson, Bob Anderson, and Louis Gruenberg; also, a TMs (copy) address by Anderson, 14 l.; and a newsclipping
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Campbell Arnoux of WTAR radio 1934 April 12-1949 Aug. 31, 3 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé 1920 Oct. 1-1929 April 10, 21 items (Box 1)
  concerning a proposal that evening papers be allowed to use certain releases of Associated Press intended for Sunday morning; includes a "Statement for the Committee" studying the question
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people whose last names begin with "Ba" through "Bi" 1919 Dec. 30-1949 Jan. 1, 38 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people whose last names begin with "Bl" through "Bo" 1924 Sept. 8-1945 May 8, 32 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people whose last names begin with "Br" 1919 Dec. 8-1946 Sept. 30, 34 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people whose last names begin with "Bu" through "By" 1931 Aug. 21-1949 Oct. 19, 34 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Stringfellow Barr of U.Va., University of Chicago, and St. John's College 1925 Oct. 16-1930 Dec. 4, 53 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Stringfellow Barr 1931 Jan. 3-1948 March 22, 89 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with James S. Barron and family 1929 Jan. 23-1941 Nov. 18, n.d., 8 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence to Louis I. Jaffé from Bernard M. Baruch 1933 July 6-1946 March 31, 5 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with John S. Battle, Senator, Charlottesville, Va. 1949 Aug. 4 & 18, 2 items (Box 2)
- D.W. Bell, Under Secretary of the Treasury to Louis I. Jaffé 1945 May 16, TLS (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Mrs. Herbet (Janet Weil) Bluetenthal 1919 Dec. 6-1950 Jan. 12, 6 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with the Rev. W. Russell Bowie, Grace Episcopal Church, N.Y.C. 1925 May 14-1930 April 12, 6 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Michael Bradshaw of The Danville Register and later the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette 1937 Jan. 2-1944 Aug. 6, 4 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Dr. Philip Alexander Bruce and his daughter, Philippa Bruce 1923 June 16-1930 Feb. 4, 9 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Mrs. Philip Alexander Bruce (Betty Taylor) 1923 Oct. 16-1936 Nov. 18, 8 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with John Stewart Bryan of the Richmond News-Leader and President of W and M 1919 Jan. 1-1941 Dec. 31, 39 items (Box 2)
- Stewart Bryan, Jr., to Louis I. Jaffé 1936 March 2 & 14, 2 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Harry Flood Byrd 1924 March 24-1930 Jan. 5, 61 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Harry Flood Byrd 1930 May 2-1947 Sept. 30, 55 items (Box 2)
- Richard Evelyn Byrd, Attorney, to Louis I. Jaffé 1922 March 20 & 1925 June 8, 2 items (Box 2)
- Admiral Richard Evelyn Byrd to Louis I. Jaffé 1931 March 23 & 30, 2 items (Box 2)
- James F. Byrnes to Louis I. Jaffé 1945 May 25, TLS (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people whose last names begin with "Ca" through "Co" 1919-1947, ca. 81 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people whose last names begin with "Cr" through "Ch" 1919-1948, ca. 21 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Charles J. Calrow, architect 1921-1924, 7 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Governor Wm. E. Cameron, Editor of Virginian-Pilot before Jaffé 1919-1921, n.d., 12 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Bishop James Cannon, Jr. re: Unification 1925, 2 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Major Hundson Cary, Attorney 1923-1933, 6 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Wm. B. Causey, Norfolk City Manager 1924-1926, 7 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Lenoir Chambers, editor Ledger-Dispatch, Virginian-Pilot 1929-1932, 15 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Dr. J.A.C. Chandler, President of William and Mary College 1920-1933, 15 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with R.G. Cherry, Governor of N.C. 1931-1948, 4 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with the Chicago-Tribune Syndicate 1924, 1949, 6 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Marquis Childs, columnist 1944-1949, 7 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with W.T. Chrisitan, editor 1943, 3 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Emily Clark (Balch), editor 1922-1926, 7 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Judge H.G. Cochran of Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court 1926-1948, 14 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with O.J. Coffin 1926, 6 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with W.S. Copeland, editor 1922, 1927, 4 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with John D. Corbell, City Clerk of Norfolk 1941-1947, 8 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé re: Council of Higher Education 1941, 10 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Rev. H.H. Covington, St. Paul's Church, Norfolk 1925-1926, n.d., 5 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with W.A. Cox, Chamber of Commerce, Norfolk 1920-1921, 16 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with James Cruikshank, editor, The Post Publishing Co., Wilmington, N.C. 1923-1924, n.d., 5 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people who last name begin with "Da" through "De" 1920-1949, 23 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with various people who last name begin with "Di" through "Dw" 1921-1949, 36 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Jonathan Daniels of The News and Observer, Raleigh 1948-1949, 6 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Virginius Dabney of the News Leader and Times-Dispatch, Richmond 1927-1949, ca. 76 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Colgate Darden 1933-1949, 14 items (Box 3)
  includes a note from Mrs. Colgate (Connie) Darden
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Arthur Kyle Davis 1920-1931, 9 items (Box 3)
  re: Virginia War History Commission
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Hugh C. Davis, lawyer (father-in-law, first marriage) 1920-1931, 9 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Hugh W. Davis, lawyer (brother-in-law, first marriage) 1920-1945, 17 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Julia Johnson Davis, writer 1930-1940, 5 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Lambert Davis, Virginia Quarterly Review 1929-1936, 9 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Margaret Davis (Jaffé's first wife) 1920, 20 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Virginia Waller Davis, State Departmental News Service 1946-1949, 5 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with F. Trube Davison, Chairman, National Crime Commission 1925-1926, 3 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with J.T. Deal, House of Representatives 1921-1926, 9 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé re: W.L. Devany, Jr. Attorney 1921-1926, 2 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Alonzo T. Dill, journalist 1939-1949, 32 items (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Marjorie Stoneman Douglas, journalist 1928-1932, n.d., 5 items (Box 4)
- Correpondence of Louis I. Jaffé with W. Carey Dowd, Jr., editor 1932-1949, 10 items (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé with Alpheus W. Drinkwater 1945, 3 items (Box 4)
  re: the Wright Brothers' flight
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé re: Duke University (Trinity), Class of 1911, 30th Reunion 1941, 25 items (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Louis I. Jaffé re: Duke University Loyalty Fund 1947-1948, ca. 46 items (Box 4)
- Jaames Barron Hope to John Emmerson, Esq. 1865 Nov. 3, ALS (Box 4)
- Correspondencce of J.J. Lankes with Louis I. Jaffé, with enclosures of woodcuts 1931 June 13-1932 April 10, 4 items (Box 4)
- Christmas cards from J.J. Lankes to L.I. Jaffé with woodcuts 1934-1950, n.d., 8 items (Box 4)
- Gertrude Stein to Mr. M.A. Agelasto and two typed copies; newspaper clipping re Mr. Agelasto 1934 [Nov. 11] and 1974 April 29, ALS, 4 items (Box 4)
- Article on J.J. Lankes by [Louis Jaffé] with corrections and a note from Robert Frost 1941 Nov. 29, TMs (copy), 12 l. (Box 4)
- Bookplates by J.J. Lankes for various people 1930-1942 and n.d., 12 items (Box 4)
- Newspaper clippings re: William Faulkner 1962 July 7-15, n.d., 6 items (Box 4)
- Phi Beta Kappa Certificate of Louis Jaffé; Omicron Delta Kappa Certificate of Louis Jaffé 1922 March 29 and 1927 May 20, 2 DS (Box 4)
- Printed Material, Song books of the A.E.F., including two with illustrations 1918-1919, 4 items (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous printed material re: various subjects 1930, 1936, n.d., 4 items (Box 4)
- The Richmond Compiler, vol. 18, no. 27 1818 June 20, 1 item (Box 4)
- The Book Dial, VI, no. 4 1929, 1 item (Box 4)
  contains articles and woodcuts by J.J. Lankes
- Woodcut, "Myers House (1791), Norfolk, Virginia," by W. Bailey 1933 Dec., 1 item (Box 4)
- Photographs relating to the American Red Cross Commission to the Balkans 1918, 1919, n.d., 150 items (Box 4)
  including photos taken in Serbia, Roumania, Bulgaria, Dalmatia, Albania, Greece, and Bosnia
- Photographs of Louis I. Jaffé in uniform, of Jaffé, an of a drawing of Jaffé [1919], 1948, n.d., 3 items (Box 4)
- Photograph of a sketch of Sisley Huddleston; photogaph of Frances Newman and H.L. Mencken n.d., 2 items (Box 4)
- Unidentified photograph n.d., 1 item (Box 4)
- Photogrphs of Berlin [ca. 1919], 34 items (Box 4)
- Photographs of unidentified city n.d., 9 items (Box 4)
  possibly a Balkan city, ca. 1918 or 1919
- B.A. degree of Louis I. Jaffé from Trinity College, N.C. 1911 June 7, DS
- Commission of Louis I. Jaffé as Second Lieutenant in the Field Artillery Section, Officers' Reserve Corps of the Army of the United States 1917 Nov. 8, DS
- Commission of Louis Jaffé as Second Lieutenant in the Aviation Section of the Signal Officers Reserve Corps of the Army of the United States 1918 Feb. 2, DS
- Commission of Louis I. Jaffé as Inspector in the American National Red Cross with assimilated rank of Captain in the Army of the United States 1919 May 31, DS
- Pulitzer Prize Certificate in Journalism 1929 June 5, DS
- Headline type which reads "Willkie Elected"